What's a well-meaning decision by one person is outright censorship to the next. What we now know is that this account, Texas Lone Star, was part of a wider Russian disinformation campaign, one that has since been taken down. Would that change your view? It would mine, because now it's a case of a coordinated campaign to sow discord. And for those of you who'd like to think that artificial intelligence will solve all of our problems, I think we can agree that we're a long way away from AI that's able to make sense of posts like this. So I'd like to explain three interlocking issues that make this so complex and then think about some ways we can consider these challenges. First, we just don't have a rational relationship to information, we have an emotional one. It's just not true that more facts will make everything OK, because the algorithms that determine what content we see, well, they're designed to reward our emotional responses. And when we're fearful, oversimplified narratives, conspiratorial explanations and language that demonizes others is far more effective. And besides, many of these companies, their business model is attached to attention, which means these algorithms will always be skewed towards emotion. Second, most of the speech I'm talking about here is legal. It would be a different matter if I was talking about child sexual abuse imagery or content that incites violence. It can be perfectly legal to post an outright lie. But people keep talking about taking down "problematic" or "harmful" content, but with no clear definition of what they mean by that, including Mark Zuckerberg, who recently called for global regulation to moderate speech. And my concern is that we're seeing governments right around the world rolling out hasty policy decisions that might actually trigger much more serious consequences when it comes to our speech. And even if we could decide which speech to take up or take down, we've never had so much speech. Every second, millions of pieces of content are uploaded by people right around the world in different languages, drawing on thousands of different cultural contexts. We've simply never had effective mechanisms to moderate speech at this scale, whether powered by humans or by technology. And third, these companies -- Google, Twitter, Facebook, WhatsApp -- they're part of a wider information ecosystem. We like to lay all the blame at their feet, but the truth is, the mass media and elected officials can also play an equal role in amplifying rumors and conspiracies when they want to. As can we, when we mindlessly forward divisive or misleading content without trying. We're adding to the pollution. I know we're all looking for an easy fix. But there just isn't one. Any solution will have to be rolled out at a massive scale, internet scale, and yes, the platforms, they're used to operating at that level. But can and should we allow them to fix these problems? They're certainly trying. But most of us would agree that, actually, we don't want global corporations to be the guardians of truth and fairness online. And I also think the platforms would agree with that. And at the moment, they're marking their own homework. They like to tell us that the interventions they're rolling out are working, but because they write their own transparency reports, there's no way for us to independently verify what's actually happening. (Applause) And let's also be clear that most of the changes we see only happen after journalists undertake an investigation and find evidence of bias or content that breaks their community guidelines. So yes, these companies have to play a really important role in this process, but they can't control it. So what about governments? Many people believe that global regulation is our last hope in terms of cleaning up our information ecosystem. But what I see are lawmakers who are struggling to keep up to date with the rapid changes in technology. And worse, they're working in the dark, because they don't have access to data to understand what's happening on these platforms. And anyway, which governments would we trust to do this? We need a global response, not a national one. So the missing link is us. It's those people who use these technologies every day. Can we design a new infrastructure to support quality information? Well, I believe we can, and I've got a few ideas about what we might be able to actually do. So firstly, if we're serious about bringing the public into this, can we take some inspiration from Wikipedia? They've shown us what's possible. Yes, it's not perfect, but they've demonstrated that with the right structures, with a global outlook and lots and lots of transparency, you can build something that will earn the trust of most people. Because we have to find a way to tap into the collective wisdom and experience of all users. This is particularly the case for women, people of color and underrepresented groups. Because guess what? They are experts when it comes to hate and disinformation, because they have been the targets of these campaigns for so long. And over the years, they've been raising flags, and they haven't been listened to. This has got to change. So could we build a Wikipedia for trust? Could we find a way that users can actually provide insights? They could offer insights around difficult content-moderation decisions. They could provide feedback when platforms decide they want to roll out new changes. Second, people's experiences with the information is personalized. My Facebook news feed is very different to yours. Your YouTube recommendations are very different to mine. That makes it impossible for us to actually examine what information people are seeing. So could we imagine developing some kind of centralized open repository for anonymized data, with privacy and ethical concerns built in? Because imagine what we would learn if we built out a global network of concerned citizens who wanted to donate their social data to science. Because we actually know very little about the long-term consequences of hate and disinformation on people's attitudes and behaviors. And what we do know, most of that has been carried out in the US, despite the fact that this is a global problem. We need to work on that, too. And third, can we find a way to connect the dots? No one sector, let alone nonprofit, start-up or government, is going to solve this. But there are very smart people right around the world working on these challenges, from newsrooms, civil society, academia, activist groups. And you can see some of them here. Some are building out indicators of content credibility. Others are fact-checking, so that false claims, videos and images can be down-ranked by the platforms. A nonprofit I helped to found, First Draft, is working with normally competitive newsrooms around the world to help them build out investigative, collaborative programs. And Danny Hillis, a software architect, is designing a new system called The Underlay, which will be a record of all public statements of fact connected to their sources, so that people and algorithms can better judge what is credible. And educators around the world are testing different techniques for finding ways to make people critical of the content they consume. All of these efforts are wonderful, but they're working in silos, and many of them are woefully underfunded. There are also hundreds of very smart people working inside these companies, but again, these efforts can feel disjointed, because they're actually developing different solutions to the same problems. How can we find a way to bring people together in one physical location for days or weeks at a time, so they can actually tackle these problems together but from their different perspectives? So can we do this? Can we build out a coordinated, ambitious response, one that matches the scale and the complexity of the problem? I really think we can. Together, let's rebuild our information commons. Thank you. (Applause)
Qu'est-ce qui sépare une décision bien intentionnée de la censure ? Nous savons à présent que ce compte, Texas Lone Star, faisait partie d'une campagne russe de désinformation qui a été démantelée depuis lors. Cela change-t-il votre opinion ? Ça influencerait la mienne car il s'agit d'une campagne orchestrée pour semer la zizanie. Et pour ceux et celles qui pensent que l'intelligence artificielle va résoudre tous nos problèmes, Nous sommes tous d'accord pour dire que le temps où l'IA pourra comprendre ça n'est pas encore venu. Je vais d'abord vous présenter trois enjeux entrelacés qui rendent tout ça si compliqué. Ensuite, je vous proposerai quelques manières de réfléchir à ces défis. D'abord, notre relation à l'information n'est pas rationnelle, elle est émotionnelle. Il n'est pas vrai que davantage de faits vont amender les choses car les algorithmes déterminent ce que nous voyons, ils sont conçus pour récompenser nos réactions émotionnelles. Or, quand on a peur, les narrations simplifiées à outrance, les théories de conspiration et les termes qui diabolisent l'autre sont encore plus efficaces. De surcroît, le modèle de fonctionnement de ces plateformes est basé sur l'attention. Ça signifie que leurs algorithmes sont conçus pour favoriser l'émotion. Ensuite, la plupart des discours que j'évoque sont légaux. La situation serait différente si on parlait d'images de pédophilie ou de contenu incitant à la violence. Il est parfaitement légal de poster un mensonge patent. Toutefois, on continue de censurer les contenus problématiques ou nuisibles sans définition claire de ce que ça signifie. Mark Zuckerberg n'y échappe pas quand il plaide en faveur d'une réglementation mondiale des discours. Je crains que les gouvernements partout dans le monde mettent en place des décisions politiques précipitées qui pourraient en réalité générer des conséquences bien plus graves en matière d'expression. Même si nous pouvions décider quels contenus conserver ou éliminer, nous n'avons jamais eu tant de contenus. Chaque seconde, des millions de contenus sont téléchargés partout dans le monde, dans des langues différentes et basés sur des contextes culturels multiples. Nous n'avons aucun mécanisme efficace pour modérer les discours à cette échelle, que ce soit avec des humains ou de la technologie. Troisièmement, ces sociétés, Google, Twitter, Facebook, WhatsApp, font part d'un écosystème d'information plus vaste. On a tendance à leur faire porter le blâme mais en fait, les médias et les représentants politiques peuvent jouer un rôle aussi important pour amplifier les rumeurs et les conspirations qui les arrangent. Nous aussi, nous sommes susceptibles de diffuser du contenu trompeur sans le vouloir. On accentue la pollution. Nous cherchons tous un remède miracle. Mais ça n'existe pas. Toute solution devra être mise en place à une échelle massive, celle d'Internet, et les plateformes en fait, sont habituées à cette échelle. Mais pouvons-nous et devrions-nous les autoriser à gérer ces problèmes ? Certes, elles essaient. Nous sommes presque tous d'accord de ne pas souhaiter voir des multinationales devenir les gardiens de la vérité et de l'équité sur Internet. Les plateformes seront d'accord aussi, je crois. Actuellement, elles sont en train de s'accorder des bons points. Elles nous disent que leurs interventions sont efficaces. Mais elles rédigent elles-mêmes leurs rapports sur leur transparence. Il n'y a donc aucun moyen indépendant pour vérifier les faits. (Applaudissements) Pour être franche, la plupart des changements que nous observons ont lieu après une enquête journalistique et la mise à nu de preuves de biais ou de contenus qui enfreignent les règles de fonctionnement. Bien sûr, ces entreprises doivent jouer un rôle crucial dans le processus mais elles ne peuvent pas le contrôler. Qu'en est-il alors des gouvernements ? Beaucoup fondent leur dernier espoir dans une réglementation mondiale pour rendre notre écosystème propre. Mais les politiciens peinent à rester à jour avec la vélocité de l'évolution technologique. Pire, ils travaillent dans le noir car ils n'ont pas accès aux données pour comprendre ce qu'il se passe sur ces plateformes. Et puis, en quel gouvernement pourrions-nous faire confiance ? La réaction doit être mondiale et pas au niveau national. Le maillon manquant, c'est nous. Nous, femmes et hommes qui utilisons ces technologies tous les jours. Saurons-nous concevoir une nouvelle infrastructure pour véhiculer une information de qualité ? Je pense que oui. J'ai quelques idées pour y arriver. D'abord, si nous sommes déterminés à engager le public, Wikipedia pourrait être une source d'inspiration. Ils ont montré que c'est faisable. Ce n'est pas parfait mais ils ont démontré qu'avec les structures adéquates, une vision mondiale et une transparence totale, on peut construire quelque chose qui gagnera la confiance du public. Nous devons trouver un moyen de puiser dans la sagesse collective et l'expérience de tous les utilisateurs, particulièrement les femmes, les personnes de couleur et les minorités. Pourquoi ? Parce qu'ils sont spécialisés dans la haine et la désinformation dès lors qu'ils sont la cible de ces campagnes depuis si longtemps. Cela fait des années qu'ils sonnent l'alarme mais personne ne les écoute. Cela doit changer. Est-il possible de construire un Wikipedia de la confiance ? Comment les utilisateurs pourraient-ils nous nourrir de leurs idées ? Des idées au sujet des décisions complexes de la modération de contenu. Un retour quand les plateformes décident de mettre en œuvre des changements. Ensuite, l'expérience que les gens ont de l'information est personnalisée. Mon fil de Facebook est différent du vôtre. Vos recommandations Youtube sont différentes des miennes. Ceci rend impossible l'analyse en profondeur des informations vues par les gens. On pourrait imaginer de créer une sorte de répertoire ouvert pour les données anonymisées qui prenne en considération vie privée et éthique. Imaginez le potentiel de compréhension issu de la création d'un réseau mondial de citoyens engagés qui souhaitent faire don de leurs données sociales à la science. Nous ignorons en effet les conséquences à long terme de la haine et de la désinformation sur l'état d'esprit et les comportements. Et ce que nous en savons provient d'études réalisées aux États-Unis, alors que le problème est mondial. Nous devons aussi remédier à ça. Troisièmement, comment relier toutes les parties ? Aucun secteur seul, encore moins une ONG, une start-up ou un gouvernement ne pourra résoudre ça. Mais de nombreuses personnes intelligentes dans le monde s'attaquent à ces défis dans les salles de rédaction, la société civile, le monde académique, les communautés activistes. En voici quelques-uns. Certains élaborent des indicateurs de crédibilité des contenus. D'autres vérifient les faits pour dégrader le taux de référencement des allégations, vidéos et images fausses. J'ai participé à la création d'une ONG, First Draft, qui collabore avec des salles de rédaction dans le monde pour les aider à élaborer des programmes collaboratifs d'investigation. Dennis Hillis, un programmateur, conçoit un nouveau système appelé The Underlay, qui sera l'archive de toutes les déclarations publiques de faits reliées à leurs sources afin que le public et les algorithmes puissent mieux évaluer ce qui est crédible. Des éducateurs dans le monde testent diverses techniques pour aiguiser l'esprit critique des gens par rapport aux contenus. Tous ces efforts sont impressionnants mais ils sont dans des silos et la plupart sont lamentablement sous-financés. Des centaines de personnes brillantes travaillent dans ces entreprises mais à nouveau, leurs efforts ne sont pas consolidés car ils développent des solutions différentes aux mêmes problèmes. Comment associer ces personnes dans un seul lieu physique, pendant quelques jours ou semaines, pour leur permettre de réfléchir ensemble à ces problèmes mais avec leur propre perspective ? Est-ce possible ? Est-il possible de créer une réponse ambitieuse et coordonnée, à la hauteur de l'échelle et de la complexité de ce problème ? J'en suis convaincue. Ensemble, reconstruisons nos fondations communes de l'information. Merci. (Applaudissements)